A Guide to the Virginia Hills Citizens Association Papers, 1955-2015
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Virginia Hills Citizens Association Papers, 1955-2015
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-33
2.0 linear feet
The Virginia Hills Citizens Association Papers consist of 2.0 linear feet, span the years 1955-2015, and consist of meeting minutes and community newsletters.
Virginia Hills Citizens Association (Alexandria, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donation from the Virginia Hills Citizens Association (VHCA) through Doug Boulter. Boulter was president of VHCA from 2000-2006 and again from 2008-2010.
Historical and Biographical Information
Virginia Hills is a community of about 750 homes that is located in the eastern portion of Fairfax County, Virginia. It is roughly bounded by the community of Wilton Woods, Telegraph Road, Lee District Park, and South Kings Highway. It belongs to Fairfax County's Lee District. The Virginia Hills Citizens Association also serves 90 additional homes in Country Club Estates, Glassellwood, and parts of Groveton, small adjoining communities that did not have citizens associations.
Virginia Hills was built on farmland and developed by builders Banks and Lee and realtor Art Post between 1951 and 1956. The land was zoned R-3 (three dwelling units per acre) and R-4 (four dwelling units per acre). While the original houses were small ramblers, many have since been added onto and renovated.
On September 16, 1952, 71 residents of Virginia Hills met and voted for the adoption of the by-laws forming the Virginia Hills Citizens Association (VHCA). The first Echo was published as a single sheet circular on June 16, 1953 with neither name nor advertising. It reported the admission of the VHCA into the Federation of Citizens Associations of Fairfax County.
The work of the citizens association over the years involved obtaining street lights, sidewalks, new street signs, and bus service for their residential community. The Association fought commercial development on Telegraph road and prevented townhouses from being built on land that is now Stoneybrook, Vantage, Kings Landing, and the intersection of Franconia and Telegraph Roads. VHCA helped bring about the conversion of the old gravel pit behind the school into Lee District Park. Until 1975, VHCA put on the annual 4th of July fireworks display, until Fairfax County took over. The month-to-month activities of the Association have included Candidates Nights in election years, social events, a teen organization, and, from 1964 to the mid-1980s, award of a college scholarship to a Virginia Hills senior.
In 1985, VHCA became dormant due to lack of interest among community members. The Citizens Association was reorganized and restarted in September 1991 to address the neighborhood problems of crime, cut-through traffic, and gypsy moths and to interface with local government.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Meeting Minutes, 1991-2000, Box 1
This series consists of minutes from meetings of the Virginia Hills Citizens Association from 1991 to 2000.
Series 2: Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1955-2015, Boxes 2-3
This series consists of community newsletters published and distributed by the Virginia Hills Citizens Association from 1955 to 2015 (years missing). Note, the newsletters from 2009 to 2015 were not part of the donation. They were downloaded from the Virginia Hills Citizens Association website (http://www.virginiahills.org/index.html) by library staff in 2015.
Arrangement
Series 1: Meeting Minutes, 1991-2000, Box 1
Series 2: Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1955-2015, Boxes 2-3
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Country Club Estates in Alexandria, Virginia (Fairfax County); Glassellwood in Alexandria, Virginia (Fairfax County); Groveton in Alexandria, Virginia (Fairfax County); Virginia Hills in Alexandria, Virginia (Fairfax County); Virginia Hills Citizens Association
Container List
- Series 1: Minutes of Meetings, 1991-2000
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 2: Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1955-2015
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Newsletters: Virginia Hills Echo, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 19)